# Jonathan Costa de Abrantes

Brazilian, Single, 27 years old

Brasília - DF

Cell phone: (61) 98361-1616

E-mail: jonathan.abrantesc@gmail.com

### ABOUT ME

With over nine years of experience in Information Technology, I began my career by progressing from an internship to a technical leadership role at Sicoob. Subsequently, I gained experience as a DevOps Analyst at 4Linux, dealing with Linux systems administration and process automation. Currently, I work as a Senior DevOps Consultant at Agap2IT Portugal, working with advanced technologies such as Kubernetes, Docker, Ansible, Jenkins, and monitoring tools such as Nagios and Grafana.

# FORMAÇÃO ACADÊMICA

- Bachelor of Information Systems (UPIS), completed in 2019.
- Computer Technician (Centro de Ensino Profissional), completed in 2013.

# EXPERIÊNCIA PROFISSIONAL

# 2023-Current - Agap2IT Portugal

## **Job Title: Senior DevOps Consultant**

Responsible for SAAS and IAAS environments of technologies related to SmartCities in regions of Spain. Using Docker in IAAS and Kubernetes in SAAS.

# Technologies:

- Kubernetes Openshift;
- Automated deployments to VMs;
- Ansible;
- Jenkins;
- Ansible/Ansible AWX;
- Docker/Docker Compose;
- Nagios;
- Grafana;
- Splunk.

# 2022-2023 – 4Linux

### **Job Title: DevOps Analyst**

Responsible for maintaining a cluster of containers that have the largest inventory park of workstations in the world using the OCS Inventory solution for an environment of hundreds of thousands of machines, responsible for changes in the source code of the solution according to the needs of the Caixa Econômica Federal using PERL. Responsible for maintaining the internal infrastructure of 4Linux, managing the company's solutions also in cloud container clusters (AWS, GCP and Azure). Responsible for teaching classes on technologies related to DevOps and being a content creator on the internal Blog and Twitch.

# Technologies:

- Docker/Docker Compose/Docker Swarm;
- AWS and GCP Cloud management;
- Kubernetes EKS;
- CI/CD Jenkins;
- Linux System Administrator;
- Ansible/Ansible AWX;
- Edition and creation of Debian images for Caixa's park;
- Edition of OCS modules for Caixa's park inventory;
- Development and implementation of projects in Caixa's environment;
- Cloud (AWS, GCP, Azure e OCI), Linux and OpenSource Solutions trainer;
- Blog and Twitch content creator.

### • 2016-2018- Sicoob

# **Job Title: Infrastructure and Networks Assistant**

Professional growth in the technical support area, starting as an intern and becoming the technical leader of a team of 9 people, managing the team and working in the support area as well. At the same time responsible for the infrastructure area of Sicoob Payments, operating Linux servers, CI/CD pipeline and primarily responsible for the area of moving/sending/receiving files through the IBM Connect Direct tool.

# Technologies:

- Infrastructure as code: Ansible;
- Administration of OVM (Oracle VM Manager);
- Automation of virtual machines using Ansible;
- Installation and administration of application servers (Jboss and Tomcat);
- Source code management tools (Git and Bitbucket);
- Jenkins continuous integration tool;
- Monitoring tools (Zabbix, Nagios and Grafana);
- Installation/Configuration/Administration of Openshift;
- Troubleshooting in mission-critical environments;
- Automation of tasks and batch processes developing scripts in Powershell and Bash;
- Administration of Linux operating systems (Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7, Oracle Linux 7), AIX (6.1 and 7.1), Windows, Windows Server and MacOs;
- Automation of Windows/Linux/Aix processes;
- Moving files: IBM File Agent/Connect and LocalCarrier;
- AD Management (Users, Groups, Permissions, GPO, WSUS, DHCP, DNS);
- Technical support in first, second and third level categories;
- Maintenance and assembly of wired and wireless networks;
- Configuration and management of PABX extensions;
- Audioconference and videoconference management;
- Printer management;
- Outsourcing of supplies;
- Management of the GFI antispam tool;
- Assembling advice on purchases of IT equipment, licenses and software;
- Teach Windows server administration activities (AD/GPO/DNS) and daily Sicoob's Helpdesk activities;
- Integration projects of the Comunix tool in the Cabal Brasil/Sicoob environment.

## • 2014-2015 - SESI

### **Job Title: Intern**

Responsible for the technical support tasks of SESI Taguatinga.

# Technologies:

- Microsoft Windows 7;
- MikroTik Routers and Wireless;
- Audioconference and videoconference management;

- Printer management with Windows Server;
- Assembling advice on purchases of IT equipment, licenses and software;
- Active Diretory;
- Linux Debian.

#### CERTIFICATIONS

- Scrum Foundation Professional Certificate (Certiprof).
- Google Cloud Essentials (Google).
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2023 Certified Foundations Associate (Oracle).

# **LANGUAGES**

- Portuguese (Native).
- English (Advanced).
- **Spanish** (Intermediary).

#### **COURSES**

#### Containers - Orchestration

- **DevOps Ninja: Docker, Kubernetes, and Rancher** (Udemy | Issued in November 2021 19 Hours).
- **Kubernetes: Pods, Services, and ConfigMaps** (Alura | Issued in April 2022 8 Hours).
- **Kubernetes: Deployments, Volumes, and Scalability** (Alura | Issued in August 2022 8 Hours).
- **Kubernetes for the Absolute Beginners Hands-on** (Udemy | Issued in February 2023 6 Hours).
- **Docker: Creating and Managing Containers** (Alura | Issued in March 2022 10 Hours).
- **Docker Swarm: Container Orchestration** (Alura | Issued in June 2022 12 Hours).
- Amazon EKS: Managing Containerized Applications with Kubernetes (Alura | Issued in September 2022 - 6 Hours).
- Containers Fundamentals (4Linux | Issued in August 2022 20 Hours).
- Helm Kubernetes Packaging Manager for Developers and DevOps (Udemy | Issued in July 2023 6 Hours).
- OpenShift for Absolute Beginners Hands-on (Udemy | Issued in July 2023 3 Hours).

# • IaC-Infrastructure as Code

- Automation Specialist with Ansible (4Linux | Issued in August 2022 40 Hours).
- Ansible: Your Infrastructure as Code (Alura | Issued in April 2022 12 Hours).
- Terraform: Automate Infrastructure in the Cloud (Alura | Issued in April 2022 8 Hours).
- Infrastructure as Code: Terraform and Kubernetes (Alura | Issued in January 2023 6 Hours).
- Vagrant: Managing Virtual Machines (Alura | Issued in April 2022 12 Hours).

#### Cloud

- Cloud Services Administrator: AWS, GCP, Azure (4Linux | Issued in March 2023 40 Hours).
- Ultimate AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner (Udemy | Issued in June 2022 19 Hours).
- Deploy on Amazon EC2: High Availability and Scalability of an Application (Alura | Issued in April 2022 10 Hours).
- Amazon Lightsail: Demystifying the Cloud (Alura | Issued in April 2022 8 Hours).
- Azure: Managing Kubernetes with AKS and ACR (Alura | Issued in April 2022 12 Hours).
- Amazon ECS: Managing Docker on the AWS Cloud (Alura | Issued in April 2022 8 Hours).

# • CI/CD

- **Git and Github: Control and Share Your Code** (Alura | Issued in April 2022 6 Hours).
- **Git and GitHub: Repository, Commit, and Versions** (Alura | Issued in January 2023 8 Hours).
- **Git and Github: Branching Strategies, Conflicts, and Pull Requests** (Alura | Issued in January 2022 8 Hours).
- **Gitlab CI and Docker: Continuous Delivery Pipeline** (Alura | Issued in August 2022 8 Hours).
- **Jenkins and Docker: Continuous Delivery Pipeline** (Alura | Issued in April 2022 12 Hours).
- Continuous Delivery: Reliability and Quality in Software Deployment (Alura | Issued in April 2022 8 Hours).
- Continuous Integration: Higher Quality and Less Risk in Development (Alura | Issued in April 2022 6 Hours).

### DevOps

- **DevOps Fundamentals** (LinkeDin Learning | Issued in October 2021 2 Hours).
- **DevOps Essentials** (4Linux | Issued in September 2021 20 Hours).
- DevOps Foundation (Estabilis Academy | Issued in September 2022 2 Hours).
- **Elite DevOps Journey** (Fabrício Veronez | Issued in January 2023 10 Hours).

## • Linux

- Linux System Administrator (Alura | Issued in August 2022 40 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 1: Evolution and Distributions (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 2: Open Source Software and Licensing (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 3: Command Line Basics (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 4: Using the command line to get help (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 5: Directories and Listing Files and managing files (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).

- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 6: Archiving Files on the Command Line (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 7: Searching and Extracting Data from Files (Alura | Issued in September 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 8: Turning Commands into a Script (Alura | Issued in September 2022 5 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 9: Understanding Computer Hardware (Alura | Issued in September 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 10: Where Data is Stored (Alura | Issued in September 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 11: Your Computer on the Network (Alura | Issued in September 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux LPI Essentials Certification Part 12: Security and File Permissions (Alura | Issued in September 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux I: Getting to Know and Using the Terminal (Alura | Issued in March 2022 4 Hours).
- Linux II: Programs, Processes, and Packages (Alura | Issued in March 2022 8 Hours).
- **Linux Fundamentals** (4Linux | Issued in August 2021 20 Hours).
- Linux Essentials (4Linux | Issued in August 2021 20 Hours).

# Monitoring and Other

- Service Management: Roles and Processes of IT Infrastructure (Alura | Issued in April 2022 10 hours).
- **Grafana and Telegraf: Real-time Monitoring** (Alura | Issued in August 2022 10 hours).
- NGINX: Web Server, Reverse Proxy, and API Gateway (Alura | Issued in January 2023 6 hours).
- PCI DSS Advanced Mode (1st Secure | Issued in February 2020 2 hours).

# REALIZAÇÕES

- Leadership in managing helpdesk teams.
- Leadership in implementing the Print Outsourcing System (First Place in the 2017 Most Successfully Implemented Actions Program for Cost Reduction).

## **PROJETOS**

 Content Creator - 90DaysOfDevOps. https://www.90daysofdevops.com/#/2022

90DaysOfDevOps is a free and open project that aims to teach new skills about culture and technologies in the DevOps world for the community that already works and wants to work with DevOps. My responsibility is to translate all the content from English to Portuguese in order to increase the consumption of professionals whose native language is Portuguese, to facilitate and expand the DevOps community.

- Linux;
- Script Bash;
- Python:
- Azure;

- Git;
- Docker;
- Kubernetes;
- Terraform;
- Ansible;Ansible AWX;
- Jenkins;

- Jenkins;
  Github Actions;
  ArgoCD;
  ELK, Logstash and Kibana;
  FluentD and FluentBit;
  Grafana;
  Go.